A Guide to the Rockefeller University records, Vice President, Douglas Whitaker FA823
Rockefeller Archive Center
Rockefeller University records, Vice President, Douglas Whitaker
1954-1973
Rockefeller Archive Center
Whitaker, Douglas Merritt
Rockefeller University
Rockefeller Institute for Medical Research
FA823
0.38 Cubic Feet 1 letter document box
1 box.
Biographical/Historical note
The newly adopted By-Laws of 1953 provided for an elected Vice-President who was a member of the Board of Trustees. Thomas Milton Rivers was elected the first Vice-President of the newly constituted Board of Trustees and served as Director of The Institute, Director of the Department of Laboratories and Director of the Hospital until his retirement in 1955.
August 1955 amendments to the By-Laws abolished the elected Vice-President and the requirement which provided that he be a member of the Board of Trustees and called for one or more appointed Vice-Presidents. Further amendment, January 25, 1956 provided that the Board of Trustees elect one or more Vice-Presidents to discharge such functions as may be assigned to them by the President or by resolution duly accepted at any meeting.
Between 1955 and 1959 Frank Lappin Horsfall, Jr. held the position of Vice-President for Clinical Studies; between 1955 and 1964 Douglas Whitaker served as Vice-President for Administration (between 1961-64 changed to Vice-President for Academic Administration). In 1964/65 Maclyn McCarty was elected Vice-President with special responsibilities in the clinical sciences. He is at the same time, Physician-in-Chief. In 1965 Carl Pfaffmann was elected Vice-President and Professor to develop a program of research and graduate instruction in the behavioral and social sciences. In 1969/70 a third Vice-President was added. This position carries with it the role of Secretary to the Board of Trustees and was filled by Charles Eugene Sunderlin.
In 1972 the University trustees elected Rodney W. Nichols to a new post of Vice-President for Program planning. He had been the first Director of the Office of Program Planning and Development.
In 1973 Albert Gold was named Vice-President for Academic Resources. As Vice-President he also retains his responsibilities relating to Junior faculty (Director of Postdoctoral Affairs) with additional duties in connection with organization, operation and planning at the University.
In 1974, effective September 15, Maclyn McCarty retired as Physician-in-Chief of the Hospital, which post was then filled by Dr. Attalah Kappas.
June 30, 1976 Eugene Sunderlin retired as vice-president of the RU.
June 1978 Dr. Albert Gold resigned from the University and October 1978 Drs. McCarty and Pfaffmann having reached retirement age resigned their positions as Vice-President. Mr. Rodney Nichols was elected to a new position of executive Vice-President and Mr. David J. Lyons was elected to a new position as Vice-President and Controller with new managerial responsibilities.
File Plan note
Former Classification: I 343
Conditions Governing Access note
This collection is open for research. Brittle or damaged items are available at the discretion of the RAC.
Biographical / Historical
Vice President, 1955-1964
Arrangement
Arranged by file type.
Scope and Contents
Contains subject files, correspondence and photographs.
- Subject files (Box 1)
  - American Philosophical Society, 1963-1964
    Scope and Contents note
    Correspondence with Richard H. Shryock, James Flexner and Detlev Bronk concerning Flexner, Rivers, Opie and Sabin papers.
  - Benison, Saul, 1961
    Correspondence on use of Simon Flexner papers.
  - Buildings and grounds, 1958-1959
    Primarily correspondence with Bernard Lupinek in regard to building improvements and estimated costs.
  - Ettinger Program for Creative Writing, 1963-1964
  - Housing and community development, 1959-1961
    Plans for joint apartment building with Memorial Hospital and decision to sell share of property to Memorial Hospital. Exploratory talks on a suggested community center.
  - Journal of Cell Biology, 1962-1973
    Minutes, costs and memoranda on production costs.
  - Medical electronics (Dr. V.K. Zworykin)
  - Naessens, Gaston
    Newspaper stories claiming a cure for leukemia and claiming an invitation from Rockefeller Institute.
  - New York Center for Biomathematical Research
    Space estimates and preliminary leases.
  - Safety, 1961
    Particularly in reference to accident in Armin Braun laboratory.
  - Visiting Day for Schools, 1954-1966
- Correspondence files (Box 1)
  - Kimball, Lindsley F., 1959-1963; 8 items
- 4 prints of Whitaker, taken by Eugene H. Kone (Neg #7132-7), 1957 March 20; 1 folder (Box 1)